<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-10T20:43:22+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/feed.xml</id><title type="html">virtual book</title><entry><title type="html">what I’m doing now #9</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now-feb-1-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what I’m doing now #9" /><published>2025-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now-feb-1-2025"><![CDATA[<p>Biking around East Vancouver, reading <em>The Ginger Man</em>, finding Z a new apartment, and trying to become a planner.
<!--more--></p>

<h3 id="biking-around-east-vancouver">biking around East Vancouver</h3>

<p>Biking is a great way to achieve my daily goal of exercising.
Seattle is prohibitively hilly but Vancouver has a great network of bike routes allocated on streets with sparse car traffic.
They have a detailed PDF file available online that maps their location and marks them with useful information like incline and degree of separation from car traffic.
I came up with a great acronym to remember the street names of the main bike routes in the area: W.A.L.K.</p>

<h3 id="reading-the-ginger-man">reading <em>The Ginger Man</em></h3>

<p>I bought a copy last summer and finally started it last week.
I can see why Cormac McCarthy liked it.
It also reminds me a lot of <em>Fear and Loathing in Last Vegas</em>.
After finishing the seventh chapter I sat down and wrote an <a id="2025-01-28-the-ginger-man" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/ginger-man">initial review</a> of it.</p>

<h3 id="finding-z-a-new-apartment">finding Z a new apartment</h3>

<p>Z’s apartment in Vancouver is a spacious one bedroom with a generous balcony.
It is recently renovated with tons of integrated storage but it lacks a crucial feature: a second bedroom.
I spend a lot of time at Z’s place and when I do we often both work from home.
We have comfortable workstations at opposite corners of the living room but the distance does little when one of us actively participates in a virtual meeting.
Noisecancelling headphones help but they also encourage us to speak loudly.
And even when we both work silently it’s too easy to call out across the room to ask a question, share a thought, or make a comment.
Both of us have a habit of voicing things soon after they occur to us.
It makes for interesting conversation and for a disruptive remote work environment.</p>

<p>We’ve been keeping an eye out and finally we found a good two bedroom apartment in a lively, artsy part of East Vancouver.
It costs almost the same as Z’s current place and it offers great physical separation between the two bedrooms.
We will be sad to leave Z’s current place and the neighborhood it’s in, but we’re excited for the new chapter.</p>

<h3 id="trying-to-become-a-planner">trying to become a planner</h3>

<p>I don’t mean a city planner.
Although I do fantasize about getting involved with municipal politics later in my life.</p>

<p>I mean I am trying to get better at making and adhering to plans in general.
I get a lot of stuff done in my life through what I call <a id="2023-01-28-progress-without-planning" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/progress-without-planning">coherent impulses</a>, which have proved effective but lack certain special powers particular to planning.
I’ve been ruminating on it and noticing when people make reference to it in their way of working.</p>

<p>Kiefer mentioned in his <a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/2d0fpifQoLn230QaGjrW7w?si=c4dc3ff353e74c77"><em>Approachable Music</em></a> podcast that he keeps a to-do list and his daily routine centers on attending to it.
I assume many people follow this approach but I don’t.
I keep to-do lists but my adherance to them is erratic.
I suppose part of the problem is that many items have no inherent deadline and even those that do don’t threaten much consequence.
If I for example neglect to plan an itinerary for a trip, I can still show up and improvise as long as my flights and hotel are booked.
Without a doubt I miss out on things that require research or scheduling, but I still enjoy the fruits of spontaneity and just-in-time internet searches.
I want to reduce the losses and reduce the stress of having flying by the seat of my pants all the time.
I want to change my habit.
So I’m trying to consciously draw my attention to the benefits and override the anxious avoidance that thwarts my planning impulses.</p>

<p>Jared Henderson, a former professor and literary YouTuber, <a href="https://youtu.be/5rrJ6RReYnA?si=sHhJhHoCTYPCjJfk">mentioned</a> that he keeps a list of books he will read.
I do too but I rarely reference it when deciding which book to read next.
My methods are spontaneous and informally organized.
I try out audiobooks on Spotify and Libby and continue only if they stick.
I buy books impulsively and add them to my growing library of unreads.</p>

<p>So I’m experimenting with writing a list of books I intend to read this year.
In a way, my dabbling with planning in this way is a sort of coherent impulse.
The coherence comes from the deliberate intention to exploit the benefits of forethought and the impulse is the list of fifteen or so books I slashed out based on my current appetite and the current contents of my shelves.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="whats-next">what’s next?</h3>

<p>Keep biking.
Continue striving to do every day each of the following: work, read, exercise, write, enjoy, grow, discuss, plan, and socialize</p>

<p>Finalize Z’s moving plans.</p>

<p>Go snowboarding with Z multiple times.</p>

<p>Read the rest of <em>The Ginger Man</em> to keep up a good reading pace for the year.
After I finish it I will start <em>Malone Dies</em> unless it doesn’t <a id="2023-01-28-progress-without-planning" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/progress-without-planning">suit my appetite</a>, in which case I will pick up one of the other books on my list for 2025.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Biking around East Vancouver, reading The Ginger Man, finding Z a new apartment, and trying to become a planner.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Ginger Man (1955)</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/ginger-man" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Ginger Man (1955)" /><published>2025-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/the-ginger-man</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/ginger-man"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve read seven chapters so far.
Here are some thoughts and some excerpts.
<!--more--></p>

<p>Describing Kenneth O’Keefe’s arrival in a coastal Irish village to visit his friend Sebastian Bullion Dangerfield at his home, who greets O’Keefe at the door:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>It was a steep hill up to Balscaddoon.
Winding close to the houses and the neighbor’s eyes having a look.
Fog over the flat water.
And the figure hunched up the road.
On top it leveled and set in a concrete wall was a green door.</p>

  <p>Within the doorway, smiles, wearing white golfing shoes and tan trousers suspended with bits of wire.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>O’Keefe the visitor takes in the scenery:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Standing on the shaggy grass he gave a shrill whistle as he looked down precipitous rocks to the swells of sea many feet below.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Delightfully written.</p>

<p>Later in the book, describing Dangerfield’s tiny new home:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>[You] didn’t want to walk too fast in the front door or you’d find yourself going out the back.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I purposefully went into the book blind and I’m pleasantly surprised to learn that its writing style is quite experimental.
Stream of consciousness, unquoted dialogue mashed in.
It reminds me of Hunter S. Thompson for its style and subject matter.
Lecherous, base protagonists hurtling through life incurring all manner of debts with no regard for consequence and no semblance of restraint.
But in this one we catch more glimpses of the desperation and self-loathing that plauge rabid gluttons following their excesses and that trigger further indulgence.
Here the aftermath of one of Dangerfield’s odious bursts of verbal abuse towards his wife regarding her family:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>A very red face.
Guilt.
Grinding the teeth.
Soul trying to get out of the mouth, swallowing it back into the body.
Shut out the sobs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the first sentence of the very next paragraph Dangerfield is no longer at his house but at the bar:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>He ordered a bottle of stout and a Gold Label, telling the boy to bring him another stout and Gold Label.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is one of the objects of the author’s experimentation, time.
Even on the lower gear of dialogue the speed is set high with snappy back-and-forth, each speaker on a new line, speech bare but the quotation marks.
And when the author doesn’t want to dwell on certain scenes, he accelerates through them by compounding dialogue and action into dense morsels:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>They had one more round of stout and she turned and smiled and said that she must be going home.
And may I take you?
That’s all right.
I insist.
It’s really not necessary.
For the joy that’s in it then.
O.K.</p>

  <p>They set off along Suffolk Street, into the Wicklow Street and up the Great George’s.
And over there Thomas Moore was born.
Come in and see it, a nice public house indeed.
But I must go home and wash my hair.
But just a quick one.</p>

  <p>In they went.
The embarrassed figures looking at them and bird whispering.
The man showed them to a booth, but Mr. Dangerfield said that they were just in for a fast one.</p>

  <p>O surely, sir and it’s a grand evening. ‘Tis that.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The author slows the pace the most when he puts us inside Dangerfield’s head amongst his thoughts.
Him regarding his wife:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Long limbed Marion settled in the chair.
What makes you so tall and slender.
You raise your eyelids and cross your legs with something I like and wear sexless shoes with sexiness.
And Marion I’ll say this for you, you’re not blatant.
And when we get our house in the West with Kerry cattle out on the hills sucking up the grass and I’m Dangerfield K.C., things will be fine again.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Like moments of contemplation imply pause.
We linger with the protagonist’s thoughts.</p>

<p>It continues:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>A tram pounding by the window, grinding, swaying and rattling on its tracks to Dalkey.
A comforting sound.
Maps shaking on the wall.
Ireland a country of toys.
And maybe I ought to go over to Marion on the couch.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Soon and without warning the author teleports us into the next scene:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>In the bedroom, Dangerfield rubbing stockinged feet on the cold linoleum.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I see many similarities to Cormac McCarthy’s writing.
Most obvious is dialogue, written without attribution, qualification, or descriptive supplement.
Deft and witty, stripped of boilerplate and stilts.
McCarthy took it a step further by dropping the quotation marks.</p>

<p>Another obvious similarity to McCarthy’s writing is the grammatically irreverant use of nonsentences.
Declarative phrases stating what there is.
Subject only.
McCarthy’s use of these is ample yet perhaps more restrained and refined.
Donleavy showers us with them.
Another choice that quickens the pace of his writing.</p>

<p>A third and more subtle similitude is in the varying order that clauses appear between periods.
Sentences structured shrewdly for effect and interest.
For example, to withhold predominant details and reveal them at the end to simulate their discovery.
From the first excerpt I shared:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>On top it leveled and set in a concrete wall was a green door.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Two structural inversions in one sentence but most important is the second.
The green door’s position at the end of the sentence grants it importance, intrigue even.
We anticipate crossing the threshold.</p>

<p>Donleavy’s sentence structures are most pleasing when they eliminate commas and let his words come into direct contact.
Reproducing an excerpt I shared at the beginning:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Standing on the shaggy grass he gave a shrill whistle as he looked down precipitous rocks to the swells of sea many feet below.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s vivid in part because each detail blends into the next.
Instead of being given parts one at a time, we experience the image fluidly as one.
McCarthy uses this technique as well.
In his magnum opus <em>Blood Meridian</em> he conjures striking images from masterfully engineered sentences.
Here is the fourth sentence of the novel:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Outside lie dark turned fields with rags of snow and darker woods beyond that harbor yet a few last wolves.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sentences like these are carefully configured to eliminate cruft like “there are” and even suffixes like “–ing” that weaken verbs.
McCarthy opts for a touch of ambiguity by placing “darker woods” first instead of putting it after “beyond that” and consequently doubling “that”:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>rags of snow and beyond that darker woods that harbor yet a few last wolves.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He also rejects the “–ing” solution to the problem:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>rags of snow and beyond that darker woods harboring yet a few last wolves.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is up to the writer and their sense of style to evaluate their options.
But they have to know how to generate them in the first place.</p>

<p>A fourth technique that Donleavy and McCarthy (and Hemingway) employ is generous use of “and” to string together images.
A snippet of an excerpt from <em>The Ginger Man</em> shared earlier:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>They had one more round of stout and she turned and smiled and said that she must be going home.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>Blood Meridian</em> contains extreme examples.
Here is a single sentence near the end of chapter thirteen:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>They trampled the spot with their horses until it looked much like the road again and the smoking gunlocks and sabreblades and girthrings were dragged from the ashes of the fire and carried away and buried in a separate place and the riderless horses hazed off into the desert and in the evening the wind carried the ashes and the wind blew in the night and fanned the last smoldering billets and drove forth the last fragile race of sparks fugitive as flintstrikings in the unanimous dark of the world.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That last bit is brilliant.
Again:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>[the wind] drove forth the last fragile race of sparks fugitive as flintstrikings in the unanimous dark of the world</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews" /><category term="books" /><category term="literature" /><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve read seven chapters so far. Here are some thoughts and some excerpts.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Panic Room (2002)</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/panic-room" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Panic Room (2002)" /><published>2025-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/panic-room</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/panic-room"><![CDATA[<p>There is something skeevy and suspicious about how the writer designed Raoul, the white poor guy, and Burnham, the black poor guy, to create so lurid a contrast between them.
<!--more-->
Raoul is so cruel that he is unsympathizable while Burnham is so principled in favor of the safety of our rich white protagonists that by the end he seems more devoted to their safety than his own welfare or that of his family.
The tell that reveals the loaded hand of the writer is the movie’s failure to explore what a real living Burnham would think, feel, and do.
This evasion is reflected in the denial of Burnham’s due place as a protagonist in the story.
The movie guiltily represents him as collateral allowing innocent whites their riches and presents it as a moral tragedy, but refuses to look it in the face.
It poses questions about class disparity and then sidesteps them, invoking us to focus instead on the mortality we all share, as if this transcendence bridges the gap in material resources that makes life viable.
But notice who is rich and innocent, and who martyrs himself tragically but righteously for the morality of it all.
By acknowledging racialized socioeconomic oppression but not engaging with it honestly, this movie functions as a pressure relief valve to ease the moral guilt of neoliberal whites who feel sorry but not remorseful.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews" /><category term="movies" /><category term="white-guilt" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There is something skeevy and suspicious about how the writer designed Raoul, the white poor guy, and Burnham, the black poor guy, to create so lurid a contrast between them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what I’m doing now #8</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now-jan-22-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what I’m doing now #8" /><published>2025-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now-jan-22-2025"><![CDATA[<p>Enjoying stillness, listening to Harold Bloom interviews, watching movies, and experimenting with routines.
<!--more--></p>

<h3 id="enjoying-stillness">enjoying stillness</h3>

<p>Despite the fact I’ve only <a id="2020-01-12-ditch-books" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/ditch-books">partially</a> read <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13136146-the-listening-book"><em>The Listening Book</em></a> and <a id="2024-08-11-end-of-absence" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/end-of-absence"><em>The End of Absence</em></a>, and despite my criticism of the latter, both books helped me better savor moments of quiet and stillness.
One of my favorite things to do right now is to take a hot, silent shower and put on the vintage <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yukata"><em>yukata</em></a> I recently bought <a id="2024-12-26-japan-trip" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/japan-trip">in Japan</a>.
In my new cotton robe I move slowly around the apartment and touch things lightly as if trying not to wake someone up.
The silence is exquisite.</p>

<p>It’s strangely soothing to say nothing for a time.
Z and I sometimes practice this in the car without prior agreement.
The longer we go without saying anything, the more peaceful we feel.
I think it is possible outside of regimented meditation to reap some of its benefits by foregoing habitual self-stimulation like chatting and listening to music to make space for felt moments of clarity.
In modern life we routinely cover up the mysteriously powerful sensations our bodies are capable of generating when idle and we therefore miss out on the cathartic experience of allowing those sensations to come to the front of our awareness.</p>

<p>In retrospect this is something I’ve been learning to do over the last few years.
In 2020 I started going on runs through my neighborhood in Capitol Hill, Seattle and instead of listening to music I listened to the sound of my body striding through the unusually quiet streets of the early Covid pandemic, revelling in the unexpectedly sunny spring of that strange year.
Birds, wind, chatter, and from balconies clapping of hands and ringing of bells to thank the work of medical professionals across the globe.</p>

<h3 id="listening-to-harold-bloom-interviews">listening to Harold Bloom interviews</h3>

<p>I first encountered Harold Bloom through his words on the back cover of Cormac McCarthy’s masterpiece:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><em>Blood Meridian</em>…seems to me clearly the major esthetic achievement of any living American writer.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>His choice of the word <em>esthetic</em> piqued my interest because it was precisely the esthetic of McCarthy’s writing that had grabbed my attention one evening almost three years ago when I opened <a id="2022-05-29-the-road" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/the-road"><em>The Road</em></a> to its hundredth page and found I couldn’t put it down.
I owe <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/14417-open-the-book-to-page-ninety-nine-and-read-and-the">Ford Madox Ford</a> for encouraging the whim:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Open the book to page ninety-nine and read, and the quality of the whole will be revealed to you.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For more than a year now I’ve been reading <em>Blood Meridian</em> in bursts and every time I pick it back up I find myself listening to more interviews of Harold Bloom.
I feel inspired and challenged by his devotion to literature and insistence on copious reading and re-reading.
I am wary of the reactionary conservatism of which he has been accused, but have so far found his perspectives very thoughtprovoking.</p>

<h3 id="watching-movies">watching movies</h3>

<p>I recently watched <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Brutalist"><em>The Brutalist</em></a>.
It was good but disturbing.
It had some themes in common with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nosferatu_(2024_film)"><em>Nosferatu</em></a>, which I also watched recently and really enjoyed.
I thought the acting, the visuals, and the writing were all very good.
It is the first Robert Eggers film I’ve seen and I’m sure it won’t be the last.
I also recently watched <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panic_Room"><em>Panic Room</em></a>.
I thought it was pretty good, but the more I think about <a id="2025-01-27-panic-room" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/panic-room">how it handled themes of race and class</a> the more uncomfortable I feel about it.</p>

<h3 id="experimenting-with-routines">experimenting with routines</h3>

<p>I continue trying to wake up early and start the day with a walk through the neighborhood.
The quiet and freshness of morning is special.
I hope to make it a habit.
I think it would transform not only my daily life but it entire.</p>

<p>Another small change I am trying is to write my <a href="/vbook/now">/now</a> update more regularly.
Usually I post one every few months.
I wrote this one less than two weeks after the <a id="2025-01-11-now" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/now-jan-11-2025">previous one</a>.
To achieve this, I’m trying to write the whole update in one sitting and this is the second time I’ve done it.</p>

<p>And, as cheesy as it might sound, to promote my goal to work, read, exercise, write, enjoy, grow, discuss, plan, and socialize everyday, I’ve put those nine words on my phone’s lock screen.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="whats-next">what’s next?</h3>

<p>I’m playing soccer once a week but trying to play more.</p>

<p>Z and I are going snowboarding with friends soon.</p>

<p>I’ve been in a <a id="2023-11-30-chart-moods" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/chart-moods">mood for producing</a> but I intend to get back to reading in the next few days.</p>

<p>Despite all the movies I’ve watched recently, I still have appetite for more.
Lynch’s recent passing is already making some of my friends more interested in watching his films and I intend to take advantage of that fact.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Enjoying stillness, listening to Harold Bloom interviews, watching movies, and experimenting with routines.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to think with your body</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/think-with-your-body" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to think with your body" /><published>2025-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/think-with-your-body</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/think-with-your-body"><![CDATA[<p>Activities that occupy partial attention – like driving or cooking – make me restless.
<!--more-->
They understimulate me.
I itch for fuller engagement.
Multitasking has a bad reputation, but I find certain tasks easier and more enjoyable to do if I can direct part of my attention to a secondary task.
I can’t, for example, just sit idly while I talk on the phone.
I need to do something with my body.
It’s almost like both my body and my brain need to be engaged.</p>

<p>While I write this, I type on the keyboard the sentences I’m forming in my mind.
If my hands stop moving because I haven’t figured what I will type next, other parts of my body start moving.
My eyes flit about the living room as if searching for my next words among the furniture.
My head cocks to one side and my mouth opens slightly as if I am trying to make out a sound.
I scratch my neck as if it were itchy.</p>

<p>I am reminded of the first few sentences of my piece <a href="https://okjuan.medium.com/is-this-working-d3e75f4e204"><em>Is This Working?</em></a>:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>When I do work and I get stuck I leave my desk and wander down the hallway.
I meander and look out the window as I think lightly about the problem.
I weave through the complications crowding my thoughts until I’ve sorted them out.
Then I return to my desk and refocus on the screen.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The more I think about it, the more I notice a fast bond between my mental and physical activity.
If I recall a memory, I often see a place.
If I think of the podcast episode between Tim Ferriss and Derek Sivers, I see in my mind’s eye the sunny valley in Washington state near British Columbia that I was driving through when I listened to it.
But my memories are not always linked to the places where I had the original experience.
Sometimes they are linked to places where I’ve previously recalled and considered the memory.
This relationship between spatial images and abstract memories mirrors the interdependence between my body and my mind.
I can’t have one without the other.</p>

<p>In some ways, <a id="2024-12-22-ecologies-of-attention-2" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/attention-2">thought and movement</a> are two sides of the same coin.
In the quiet privacy of the shower, novel thoughts emerge from the depths of the mind.
On an ambling walk, a line of thought finds direction and picks up momentum.
Going for a run dispels clouds of anxious thought and worry like a sudden change of weather.
Our brains developed in servitude to our bodies so I suppose it’s no wonder these two are so entwined.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><category term="psychology" /><category term="thinking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Activities that occupy partial attention – like driving or cooking – make me restless.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what I am doing in 2025</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what I am doing in 2025" /><published>2025-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/my-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/2025"><![CDATA[<p>This live journal is yet another experiment inspired by the ideas I originally explored in my essay <a href="https://okjuan.medium.com/the-virtual-book-part-1-782ccd4cc360"><em>The Virtual Book</em></a>.
<!--more-->
One of the attributes of “<a id="2023-08-11-virtual-book" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/virtual-book">virtual books</a>” that most intrigues me is their <strong>dynamism</strong>, the fact that they can change over time.
It excites me not because of its practicality, but because of the artistic possibilities it creates.
As I wrote originally in <em>The Virtual Book</em> and then reproduced in <a id="2022-06-11-show-instead-of-telling" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/show-instead-of-telling">one</a> of its separated pieces on this site:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What if a memoirist publishes a piece overlaid with their revisions to show the process of expression and expose the artifice of memoir?
Or what if an English professor does the same to compare writing styles and the emotions they convey?
What if a novelist publishes a first-person novel in real time to make it feel like the character really exists and is experiencing events alongside the reader?
What if the author then goes back and rewrites previous parts of the novel to show the decay of memory and its corruption in the construction of personal narratives?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In this journal I intend to do something like the hypothetical memoirist.
Throughout the year, whenever I feel so inclined, I will write here about events that might happen, are happening, or have happened in 2025.
I think it will be interesting to juxtapose my expectations, experiences, and reflections throughout the year.
I hope it will neutralize the bias we typically grant hindsight, which is a privileged perspective but not a consummate one.</p>

<h3 id="january">January</h3>

<p><em>January 18 2024</em> –
Winter in the PNW has been unusually dry and sunny.
It’s beautiful, and joyful if you don’t stop to think about the disastrous climactic changes it might portend.</p>

<h3 id="february">February</h3>

<p><em>January 18 2024</em> –
In early February we have a couple plans for gatherings with friends.
We also intend to visit Victoria.
I look forward to it.
I’m realizing I have a positive association with February.
Perhaps because it’s the month when we usually get snow in the PNW and for a couple days our surroundings are awash in white and sunshine.</p>

<p><em>February 4 2024</em> –
As foretold the annual snowdump came down in February, this time on the very first evening of the month.
For people like me that rely on outdoor sports like soccer and biking for exercise it’s rather inconvenient but that inconvenience is more than repaid in stunning views of snowcovered mountains looming above the clouds, lit in the early sunset.
Not to mention the ease with which one could drive up one of those mountains for a weekday evening of skiing.
Diligently the neighborhood character that in the spring and summer tends to the garden in the nearby rotunda today scrapes off the snow from a sidewalk path and peppers blue salt into the gash of concrete as if to cauterize it.
I greet him and he responds with a grin <em>Living the dream!</em>
On the roads his mechanized counterpart heaves aside large mounds of snow effortlessly with its front and from its back showers its trail with salt.
I walk ten minutes to one of the sushi restaurants in the area to pick up my lunch.
Too hungry to wait until I get home I pause and stand beneath the awning outside the restaurant and drink my miso soup and watch the neighborhood go on without me on its natural rhythm.</p>

<h3 id="march">March</h3>

<p><em>February 4 2024</em> –
I have loose plans to watch <em>Mickey 17</em> with friends when it comes out in theaters.
It was written and directed by Bong Joon-Ho, who directed and cowrote the magnificent <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parasite_(2019_film)"><em>Parasite</em></a>.</p>

<h3 id="april">April</h3>

<h3 id="may">May</h3>

<p><em>February 4 2024</em> –
May is the month the European soccer season climaxes.
League and cup winners alike are crowned.
Arsenal, the team I support, are still in the running for two major honors: the English Premier League (EPL) and the UEFA Champions League.
Two days ago they defeated the reigning EPL champions by a whopping and unforeseeable 5-1 scoreline.
And yet our biggest competitor this season is not them, but Liverpool, who are six points ahead of us with a game in hand.
In early May, Arsenal will go to northern England and duel them at Anfield, Liverpool’s fortress.
<em>That</em> will probably be Arsenal’s biggest match of the season.
I start to feel a bit queasy thinking about it now, three months ahead.
It’s shocking how thrilling it is even from a thousands of miles away to support a sports team embroiled in genuine competition.</p>

<h3 id="june">June</h3>

<h3 id="july">July</h3>

<h3 id="august">August</h3>

<h3 id="september">September</h3>

<h3 id="october">October</h3>

<h3 id="november">November</h3>

<h3 id="december">December</h3>

<p><em>February 4 2024</em> –
In the spirit of living with forethought and premeditation, I suggested to my mom that we begin planning a post-Christmas trip to Mexico or Guatemala, somewhere warm.
In years past I’ve intended to buy flights for the holiday season months in advance but never managed it.
Hopefully this year.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><category term="writing" /><category term="mediums" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This live journal is yet another experiment inspired by the ideas I originally explored in my essay The Virtual Book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what I did in 2024</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/2024" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what I did in 2024" /><published>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/2024-in-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/2024"><![CDATA[<p>There are many different ways to sum up a year.
Here are some.
<!--more--></p>

<h3 id="my-2024-in-music">my 2024 in music</h3>

<p>In 2024, for the seventh year in a row, I kept a journal playlist, to which I added throughout the year songs that I listened to repeatedly.
It’s fun to let time pass and then listen back to these lists.
Music is like aroma, an instantly nostalgic medium.</p>

<iframe style="border-radius:12px margin-bottom: 15px;" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/playlist/6MuDTdPI1B6l7t2x1U2GJT?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="352" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="eager"></iframe>

<h3 id="my-2024-in-books">my 2024 in books</h3>

<p>The first song in my 2024 playlist is by Mark Lanegan, whose memoir <a id="2023-12-23-sing-backwards-and-weep" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/sing-backwards-and-weep"><em>Sing Backwards and Weep</em></a> was the first book I finished in 2024.
Books offer an incredible way to access worlds that we will never see in the flesh.
As other great <a href="/vbook/tags/memoir">memoirs</a> like <a id="2020-04-26-educated" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/educated"><em>Educated</em></a> have done for me, Lanegan’s installed in my psyche a bank of artificial memories and secondhand experiences that enrich my understanding of the world and even inform my own life decisions.
The written word is a <a id="2023-03-09-justify-writing" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/justify-writing">tremendously efficient medium</a> for conjuring these pseudoexperiences.
And to think I can absorb it as audio while I perform menial tasks like driving on the highway or cooking lunch!</p>

<p>Books are of course also an incredible way to encounter new ideas.
In <a id="2024-08-11-end-of-absence" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/end-of-absence"><em>The End of Absence</em></a> I encountered Michael Harris’s thoughtprovoking but ultimately underwhelming ideas regarding the intersecting topics of technology and attention.
Later in the year I picked up Matthew B. Crawford’s <a id="2024-12-07-world-beyond-your-head" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/world-beyond-your-head"><em>The World Beyond Your Head</em></a> after seeing Tom MacWright’s <a href="https://macwright.com/2024/07/07/world-beyond-your-head">glowing review</a> of it and with this book I was not disappointed.
As I said in my most recent <a id="2025-01-11-now" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/now-jan-11-2025">/now</a> update, Crawford’s book provoked in me a lot of reflection about what things consume my attention and how <a id="2024-12-15-ecologies-of-attention" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/attention">environ</a><a id="2024-12-15-ecologies-of-attention" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/attention">ments</a> dictate that.</p>

<h3 id="my-2024-as-journaled-on-this-site">my 2024 as journaled on this site</h3>

<p>I posted four entries in 2024:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a id="2024-02-19-now" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/now-feb-19-2024">what I’m doing now #3</a>, posted on February 19th</li>
  <li><a id="2024-04-23-now" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/now-apr-23-2024">what I’m doing now #4</a>, posted on April 23rd</li>
  <li><a id="2024-07-07-now" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/now-july-7-2024">what I’m doing now #5</a>, posted on July 7th</li>
  <li><a id="2024-09-30-now" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/now-sept-30-2024">what I’m doing now #6</a>, posted on September 30th</li>
</ul>

<p>I tried to post more often but it was difficult to do so considering the level of detail I put in each one.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There are many different ways to sum up a year. Here are some.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what I’m doing now #7</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now-jan-11-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what I’m doing now #7" /><published>2025-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/now-jan-11-2025"><![CDATA[<p>Missing Japan, losing weight, experimenting with daily routines, &amp; more.
<!--more--></p>

<h3 id="missing-japan">missing japan</h3>

<p>We just got back <a id="2024-12-26-japan-trip" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/japan-trip">from Japan</a>.
I would love to live there for a while someday, although I think it unlikely, even though they offer a six month Digital Nomad visa.
Z’s work is not remote and she wants to develop her career, so teaching English or something of the sort is not particularly useful to her.
Regardless, I am sure we will visit again.</p>

<h3 id="losing-weight">losing weight</h3>

<p>I am twenty pounds lighter than I was a year and a half ago.
I still want to lose another twenty.
I am trying to eat very consciously and exercise everyday.
I feel optimistic.</p>

<h3 id="experimenting-with-daily-routines">experimenting with daily routines</h3>

<p>For the last few days I have woken up early and immediately gone out on a walk with my coffee.
It’s a lovely way to warm up for the day and start by accomplishing my daily task of exercising.
Walking is useful for me given that I am a homebody with a remote computer job and a reliance on soccer for exercise.
After returning from my morning walks I’ve spent some time reading before getting on with my day.
An aspiration I’ve set for myself is to do each of these everyday: exercise, read, write, work, enjoy, socialize, discuss, grow, &amp; plan.
I realize they might sound cheesy, but they are distillations of more specific intentions I have for 2025.</p>

<h3 id="working">working</h3>

<p>In December I received my expected promotion to Senior Software Engineer.
It’s a milestone in my career.
The pay bump was nice if modest for industry standards, but the biggest perk is the deference I am already getting as part of the increase in my responsibilities.
I have strong opinions on how certain things should be done and I feel already a boost in persuasive power generated from my new title.
To summarize, I feel like I have more agency, and I welcome it.</p>

<h3 id="reading-writing-and-avoiding-distractions">reading, writing, and avoiding distractions</h3>

<p>Matthew B. Crawford’s <a id="2024-12-07-world-beyond-your-head" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/world-beyond-your-head"><em>The World Beyond Your Head</em></a> has provoked in me a lot of reflection about what things consume my attention and how <a id="2024-12-15-ecologies-of-attention" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/attention">environ</a><a id="2024-12-15-ecologies-of-attention" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/attention">ments</a> dictate that.</p>

<p>I recently read <a id="2024-12-19-molloy" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/molloy"><em>Molloy</em></a> by Samuel Beckett and I intend to continue with the second book in the trilogy.</p>

<p>I also resumed reading and marveling at the prose in <em>Blood Meridian</em>.
I think it appropriate to take my time with what Harold Bloom called  “the major esthetic achievement of any living American writer.”
Of course, McCarthy has since died and his legacy has begun morphing due to recent news of a very inappropriate relationship he had with a teenage girl named Augusta Britt.</p>

<h3 id="watching-movies">watching movies</h3>

<p>Last year as soon as the weather started cooling and days darkening early I started watching movies.
In the last few months I’ve watched <em>The Substance</em>, <em>Woman of the Hour</em>, <em>We Live In Time</em>, <em>The Godfather</em> and <em>The Godfather Part 2</em>, <em>The Power of the Dog</em>, <em>Killers of the Flower Moon</em>, <em>Anora</em>, <em>A Real Pain</em>, <em>Perfect Days</em>, <em>Gladiator II</em>, and <em>Punch-Drunk Love</em>.
Reviews and ratings for these are or will be on <a href="https://letterboxd.com/okjuanito/films/reviews/">my letterboxd account</a>.
Tomorrow I’m going to watch <em>The Brutalist</em>.</p>

<h3 id="following-arsenal">following Arsenal</h3>

<p>Following the English Premier League is so interesting because the competition is so fierce and sophisticated.
It is so difficult for teams to win.
It is so difficult for fans or pundits to predict what will happen.
New players arrive, old ones fall away, young ones rise into prominence.
It’s a lucrative business but it is also genuine, gripping drama.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="whats-next">what’s next?</h3>

<p>The year 2025 is a blank canvas.
We don’t have any specific plans.
Of course, it is predictable in some ways.
But perhaps more so, it is open ended.</p>

<p>I begin the year with several intentions.
Do big things at work.
Get fitter.
Lose twenty pounds.
Have more discussions with friends.
Read copiously.
Keep writing for and developing this site.
Nurture friendships.
Heal and grow.
Enjoy our DINK status.
Ruminate on longterm plans.</p>

<hr />

<p>I round the corner of another year with the intention to change my life.
Change it not majorly, but minorly.
I intend to live in the same place, work the same job, drink the same coffee.
But I want to sharpen my focus.
I intend to withhold my attention a bit more and marshall it with more discipline towards things that matter.
That doesn’t mean I will scold myself if I waste time, or spend it on unimportant things.
But I want to try everyday to dedicate <em>more</em> attention to things that matter, to things that will accumulate rather than disappear into the void like jewelry into the drain.</p>

<p>I will continue resisting idealistic aspirations towards abstract virtue, but will try to submit myself to disciplines that I trust will render concrete results.
Spending more time reading.
Waking earlier.
Avoiding cheap distractions that undermine opportunities to spend time meaningfully.
I’m not so interested in deeming time spent scrolling on instagram or passively consuming recommended YouTube videos as immoral.
It is not bad to produce nothing or learn nothing for a few minutes on a random day, but it is costly to let it become a habit.
Costly in time and in opportunity.
I don’t believe I’m particularly special but I do think there is a version of me at eightysomething years old that looks back with some sastifaction at his life’s work.
I want to do something meaningful and I know the steady progress of minutes hours and days can lead to things that irregular bouts of inspiration can imagine but never produce.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Missing Japan, losing weight, experimenting with daily routines, &amp; more.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">why context matters</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/context" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="why context matters" /><published>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/context</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/context"><![CDATA[<p>Museums underwhelm me.
<!--more-->
The task of trudging around a vast building looking at a bunch of items seems like lazily assigned homework, especially at big museums.
I need a lot more context.
One paragraph per gallery is not enough, nor is a little tag telling me what each item is or was.
Perhaps I need to start booking tours at every museum I go to.
I would feel much more engaged if I could ask questions or otherwise felt like I was <em>understanding</em> something.</p>

<p>At Tokyo National Museum, the exhibit I most enjoyed was the archaelogical one.
It sketched the ancient history of Japan in twelves paragraphs arranged in chronological order around a big room full of ceramic pots and other ancient items that have been uncovered in the region.
Most of my attention was absorbed by the information and only a little bit was given to the artifacts themselves.
Remains of archaic civilizations are interesting, but they don’t make my imagination run wild.
I need something to engage with mentally.</p>

<p>Before we went into the archaelogical exhibit, I spent most of the time on my phone.
Not distracting myself, but pouring mental energy into reading people’s opinions on Reddit regarding whether <em>Infinite Jest</em> was worth reading.
It was fun.
It made me think.
I also spent some time grumpily mulling over why I felt disinterested in the museum.
<em>Should I</em> find this format engaging?
Room after room of items displayed behind glass through which I was supposed to peer studiously and silently for a few seconds?
And when I was finished, what coherent impression was I supposed to have cobbled from eyeing an assortment of tools and trinkets presented to me with minimal context?</p>

<p>I found myself speculating on the origin of museums themselves.
Who made this format up?
The history of things often reveals obscure and obsolete reasons behind their particularities.
City planning and land zoning in America, for example, seem arbitrary and incompetently devised until you understand the cultural context they developed from.
Certain rules and norms start making a lot more sense when you understand that many American cities followed the example set by New York and that New York’s infrastructure developed to accommodate white families living in the suburbs while working in the city.
In that light, we start to see the murky reasons why transit infrastructure in American cities caters to cars first and why single family residential zoning is so common in North America.
It is only due to the ongoing housing crises that American and Canadian cities have begun to loosen restrictions to allow buildings with multiple dwellings in these areas.</p>

<p>We must resist the impulse of assuming norms and <a href="/vbook/tags/rules">rules</a> must make sense.
Things are shaped by their history, and it is the material conditions of a particular place and time that set the mold.
When the reasoning underpinning a design is not evident, and when the design seems counterproductive, there is probably a very good historical reason for it.
A very good reason for why it <em>happened</em>, that is, not for why it should still be.</p>

<p>I suspect there are very good reasons discoverable in the history of museums to explain why they are the way they are.
Whatever the reasons, they are not evident to me now, and I suspect they are obsolete.
I can imagine European aristocrats centuries ago oohing and ahhing at exotic artifacts taken from faraway worlds and imagining the fascinating “primitive” lives to which they belonged.
Perhaps for these folks simply gazing at objects plucked from the cultures that gave them their meaning was a thrill and a half, and perhaps it would be for me as well if I didn’t have access to computers, the internet, and international travel.
Perhaps if I lived back then, in their context, I would also covet these same artifacts as trophies, as precious symbols of my status in the world.
In that case I would make sure to keep it safe, still showing it off, yes, but from the safety of a glass box, alongside the rest of my collection.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><category term="history" /><category term="design" /><category term="law" /><category term="rules" /><category term="mediums" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Museums underwhelm me.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">japan trip</title><link href="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/japan-trip" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="japan trip" /><published>2024-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/japan-trip</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://okjuan.github.io/vbook/japan-trip"><![CDATA[<p>For Christmas and New Years, I went to Japan with my wife Z, my mom, my older sister, her boyfriend, and my younger sister.
<!--more--></p>

<h3 id="daily-log">Daily Log</h3>

<h4 id="saturday-12212024--sunday-12222024--tokyo-first-time-at-an-izakaya">Saturday 12/21/2024 / Sunday 12/22/2024 – Tokyo, first time at an izakaya</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Z &amp; I flew @ 12:45pm directly from Vancouver (YVR) -&gt; Tokyo (NRT)</li>
  <li>Z slept while the rest of us ate at a nearby izakaya (drinks, raw tuna, cheese pancakes, potato croquettes, chicken karaage, etc.)</li>
  <li>chocolate ice cream bar at 7 Eleven on the way back to the hotel</li>
</ul>

<p>Z &amp; I flew with Air Canada.
We upgraded to Premium Economy to avoid being stuck in a couple of middle seats.
It was expensive, but it made our flight much better.
I spent the whole flight reading and writing.
I read the first 150 pages of <em>Normal People</em> and <a id="2024-12-21-how-normal-people-think" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/normal-people">wrote about it</a>, pausing only to eat meals.
I couldn’t believe it when it was announced that we were beginning our descent.</p>

<h4 id="monday-12232024--tokyo-a-day-of-shopping">Monday 12/23/2024 – Tokyo, a day of shopping</h4>

<ul>
  <li>solo coffee nearby while Z &amp; my family ate breakfast at the hotel</li>
  <li>together took train to Shibuya City, then ate at a good conveyor belt sushi restaurant</li>
  <li>solo flat white @ The Roastery by Nozy Coffee on Cat Street</li>
  <li>solo browse MoMA Design Store &amp; other boutiques, bought tea towel from Hay</li>
  <li>solo walk thru Shibuya, fatigued from jetlag, got another coffee</li>
  <li>solo browsed robe store but did not find what I wanted</li>
  <li>with group again, bought hoodie @ Carhartt Work In Progress store</li>
  <li>bought shoes and slides @ Hoka store</li>
  <li>visit Tadao Ando’s public bathroom in Jingū-dōri Park, which was featured in the movie <em>Perfect Days</em></li>
  <li>Shibuya crossing! then very spicy ramen at a place with weird vibes</li>
</ul>

<p>I had severe allergies until the early evening.
This happens to me whenever I travel somewhere new.
In 2017 I went to Europe for the first time and I spent the first full day sneezing and oozing.
Same thing this time in Tokyo for the first 24 hours.
Reactine didn’t seem to make a difference, just had to wait it out.</p>

<h4 id="tuesday-12242024--tokyo">Tuesday 12/24/2024 – Tokyo</h4>

<ul>
  <li>arrived at Disney Sea @ 12pm</li>
  <li>rode on lots of rides, walked a lot, listened to Disney Xmas carollers</li>
  <li>subpar pizza &amp; pasta in Little Venice</li>
  <li>explored the rest of the park, rode on more rides, fought jetlag</li>
  <li>left @ 9pm, closing time</li>
</ul>

<p>The architecture and spatial planning of the theme park was really impressive.
It seemed like every corner we rounded we encountered another stridebreaking view of the park.
It reminded me of the architectural tactic of constraining the height and width of hallways to reinforce the impact of emerging into a bigger space.
It’s a method that’s been employed by Tadao Ando of Osaka and other famous architects like Frank Lloyd Wright.</p>

<h4 id="wednesday-12252024--tokyo">Wednesday 12/25/2024 – Tokyo</h4>

<ul>
  <li>solo walk through the Shimbashi area getting a couple of coffees</li>
  <li>Z &amp; I explored Ebisu on foot, stopping at a puppy store and a pharmacy</li>
  <li>cocktails @ bar EAS MOR, which had great atmosphere</li>
  <li>visited mall briefly, then dinner @ Toki Taruza withe everyone</li>
  <li>7 Eleven for snacks on the way to the hotel</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="thursday-12262024--tokyo---takayama">Thursday 12/26/2024 – Tokyo -&gt; Takayama</h4>

<ul>
  <li>get two flat whites from INCredible Coffee</li>
  <li>took bullet train @ 1pm to Takayama via Nagoya</li>
  <li>dinner at a nice sushi restaurant</li>
  <li>fell asleep by 9pm, finally cured my jetlag</li>
</ul>

<p>Tokyo station was huge and very busy.
It felt like being in a beehive.
It took me and Z a while to figure out how to pick up our tickets.
One machine gave us an error message but then we tried a machine in a different section and it worked.
Then we circled through the masses, trying to figure out which screen listed our train’s platform.
When we finally found it, we struggled to pass through the gate.
Z put in the two tickets as the ticket machine had instructed but that wasn’t enough.
We had a confusing interaction with a worker there, who we finally understood was saying to scan our IC card after inserting the tickets.
We made it through and with thirty minutes left until departure time, we lined up to buy food and drinks to take onto the train.
It’s good we came an hour early.</p>

<h4 id="friday-12272024--takayama">Friday 12/27/2024 – Takayama</h4>

<ul>
  <li>while Z had breakfast at the hotel, I walked into town and had coffee @ Brand New Day and then @ Hids’ Cafe</li>
  <li>at Miyagawa Morning Markets we bought a beef bun, a fridge magnet, two pairs of chopsticks, and two ceramic mugs</li>
  <li>pop into a cutlery store and then have lunch &amp; coffee @ Ember coffee in beautiful 150+ yearold house</li>
  <li>walk up hill to Shoren-ji Temple, enjoying the snowy scenery</li>
  <li>back in town, stop at stationery store</li>
  <li>I bought a yukata at a kimono store</li>
  <li>dinner @ ramen restaurant</li>
  <li>incredible cocktails @ Yu</li>
  <li>thirty minutes in a private onsen w/ Z at the hotel</li>
</ul>

<p>This was one of the best days of the trip.</p>

<h4 id="saturday-12282024--takayama---shirakawago---kanazawa">Saturday 12/28/2024 – Takayama -&gt; Shirakawago -&gt; Kanazawa</h4>

<ul>
  <li>solo walk over fresh snow into town for coffee @ Falò Coffee Brewers, then got cash from post office ATM, then coffee @ Ember, before returning to hotel</li>
  <li>we took the bus to Shirakawago</li>
  <li>delicious snacks and drinks from window shop on street</li>
  <li>walk through village, across pedestrian bridge over the river, to the museum, and then back</li>
  <li>coffees &amp; Baum stick</li>
  <li>we took the bus to Kanazawa, then food &amp; drinks @ Pari King nearby</li>
  <li>beer &amp; instant ramen in the hotel room</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="sunday-12292024--kanazawa">Sunday 12/29/2024 – Kanazawa</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Z &amp; I had breakfast &amp; coffee at Isotope Coffee, a beautiful space</li>
  <li>solo stroll through town listening to music and taking pictures</li>
  <li>drank coffee and <a id="2024-12-21-how-normal-people-think" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/normal-people">wrote about <em>Normal People</em></a> at Townsfolk Coffee</li>
  <li>Z met me and we walked north through Omigi Market for dinner at a fine dining restaurant called Barrier</li>
  <li>we walked through the Higashi Chaya District</li>
  <li>Z went to the Kanzawa Forus mall and I sat at a small pub to read <em>Normal People</em> &amp; drink beer</li>
  <li>we had cocktails at Furansu Cocktail Bar, which bartender at Yu in Takayama had recommended</li>
  <li>bites and drinks at Izakaya Hanagumi</li>
  <li>spent the rest of the night at Donuts Music Bar</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="monday-12302024--kanazawa">Monday 12/30/2024 – Kanazawa</h4>

<ul>
  <li>breakfast &amp; coffee at Moron Cafe</li>
  <li>visit beautiful Samurai house with an exquisite garden and a small gallery of artifacts</li>
  <li>coffee @ Townsfolk Coffee, then a brief stop at a combini store</li>
  <li>walk through to Oyama Shrine, through gardens, up to Kanazawa Castle ruins, down past Kenroku-en Garden</li>
  <li>Z took the bus to the Kanzawa Forus mall and I walked through Shiinoki Green Space back to the hotel</li>
  <li>I rested &amp; read <em>Normal People</em> in the room</li>
  <li>met Z for dinner nearby, but Love For All’s kitchen was closed so we went to The Cottage</li>
  <li>stop at Lawson, then back to hotel</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="tuesday-12312024--kanazawa---tokyo">Tuesday 12/31/2024 – Kanazawa -&gt; Tokyo</h4>

<ul>
  <li>tax to train station, where we ate and waited for our train</li>
  <li>arrived in Tokyo, train to Shimbashi, checked back into the hotel</li>
  <li>rested a couple hours at the hotel</li>
  <li>dinner @ Daigo, a fancy Shojin restaurant</li>
  <li>karaoke @ Big Echo</li>
</ul>

<p>A thunderstorm began while we were in a taxi on the way to the Kanazawa train station.
Flashes of lightning so bright I thought for a moment our driver had run a red light and triggered a super powerful automated stoplight camera.
We tried a coffee shop near the train station but it was closed for New Years, which is the biggest national holiday in Japan.
Train station was full of stores and flooded with white overhead lighting.
Cruel Summer by Taylor Swift playing in the overhead speakers.
We sat in Tully’s Coffee lounge with our bags piled around our ankles.
On the far wall a horribly sappy and nonsensical marketing poem for <em>&amp; Tea</em>.
I felt like I could be in any other manufactured commercial center around the world.
Soulless places like these often have this sort interchangeability, lack of identity.
Being there, it doesn’t feel like you’re in an actual <em>place</em>.
You’re just temporarily detained in a massproduced commercial limbo.</p>

<p>Grateful to be back in the sun.</p>

<h4 id="wednesday-01012024--tokyo">Wednesday 01/01/2024 – Tokyo</h4>

<ul>
  <li>coffee &amp; breakfast @ Starbucks</li>
  <li>visit fancy mall where teamLABS is</li>
  <li>watched Gladiator II @ 109 Cinemas</li>
  <li>ramen dinner nearby</li>
</ul>

<p>It was certainly a mistake to visit Japan in the first few days of January.
As noted all over the internet, New Years is Japan’s major national holiday and many things close not only on the first but for a week.
I’m sure Z would’ve determined this if we had been more involved in planning the trip.
Lesson learned, I suppose.</p>

<h4 id="thursday-01022024--tokyo">Thursday 01/02/2024 – Tokyo</h4>

<ul>
  <li>visit various neighborhoods including Gakugei-daigaku, Naka-meguro, &amp; Ebisu</li>
  <li>visited two more Tokyo Toilet locations, designed by Masamichi Katayama &amp;	Kashiwa Satō</li>
  <li>incredible sushi @ Standing Sushi Nemuro Hanamaru in Ginza</li>
  <li>shop @ UNIQLO Flagship store</li>
  <li>cocktails @ La France in Ginza</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="friday-01032024--tokyo">Friday 01/03/2024 – Tokyo</h4>

<ul>
  <li>visit Tokyo National Museum</li>
  <li>lunch &amp; coffee there</li>
  <li>Hello Kitty special exhibition and gift shop</li>
  <li>visit Senso-ji temple w/ Z</li>
  <li>solo walk in Asakusa area</li>
  <li>dinner w/ my friend H @ Monja Shichigosan then drinks at nearby pub</li>
</ul>

<p>I had <a id="2025-01-05-context" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/context">mixed feelings about the museum</a>.
Or, I don’t know, maybe I just needed a meal.
Or a better sleep.
Or to feel like I chose to go there.
Or to have had a period earlier in the day where I’d gotten to direct my attention to things of my choosing.
Or a period to produce something, so that I might be in a more <a id="2023-11-30-chart-moods" class="internal-site-link" href="/vbook/chart-moods">absorptive mood</a>.
That certainly makes me feel better about socializing aimlessly in the evening, when I feel like I’ve done something productive with my day.</p>

<h4 id="saturday-01042024--tokyo">Saturday 01/04/2024 – Tokyo</h4>

<ul>
  <li>solo coffee &amp; journaling @ City Bakery</li>
  <li>teppanyaki dinner w/ my mom on top floor of mall in Ginza</li>
  <li>visit the teamLAB Borderless Digital Art Museum</li>
</ul>

<p>The Digital Art Museum was really cool.
It was a dark maze on the bottom floor of a fancy mall where myriad projectors shone moving patterns and images of light on walls, floors, and ceilings.
This by itself might’ve been a gimmicky socialmedia tourist trap, but embedded throughout the large labyrinthine gallery were rooms where sculptural elements combined with light, music, and mirrors to create surreal experiences.</p>

<h4 id="sunday-01052024--tokyo---vancouver">Sunday 01/05/2024 – Tokyo -&gt; Vancouver</h4>

<ul>
  <li>check out but leave bags at hotel</li>
  <li>solo cortado from Brooklyn Roasters in Ginza</li>
  <li>solo browse flea market &amp; buy orange tinted glass to use for cappuccinos at home</li>
  <li>pick up bags at hotel and take train to Narita</li>
  <li>flew directly @ 6pm from Tokyo (NRT) -&gt; Vancouver (YVR)</li>
</ul>

<p>My intention was to browse Hands and Itoya in Ginza, but I came across the flea market when I stopped for coffee by Ginza station.
There were dozens of stalls selling ceramics, porcelain, kimonos, jackets, bluedyed fabrics, and so on.
The orange tinted glass I bought was only 400 yen, less than three dollars in USD, and I could see it selling for tens times the amount at trendy stores in the USA and Canada.
I’m still sour about going to the East Vancouver “Flea Market” to find they charge an <em>admission fee</em> and sell priced up secondhand and vintagestyled clothing.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><category term="travel" /><category term="cities" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For Christmas and New Years, I went to Japan with my wife Z, my mom, my older sister, her boyfriend, and my younger sister.]]></summary></entry></feed>